Michelle Fullwood

about

Quincy, MA maf@mit.edu (716) 241-1888 michelleful.github.io github.com/michelleful

programming

Python, Django, Flask SpaCy, gensim, PyTorch, Spark JavaScript, VueJS, iQuery SQL, git

languages

native English advanced French Mandarin intermediate Arabic Japanese elementary Hungarian Hieroglyphic Egyptian

awards

2011 NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Cornell University 2004 Merrill Scholar 2001 College Scholar 2000 Dean's Scholar 2002, 2004 Achievement Awards in Arabic 2000-2004 Dean's List Government of Singapore 2000 PSC Overseas Merit Scholarship

National Science Foundation

community involvement

Co-organizer **Boston Python** Speaker PyCon 2015, 2017 PyData NYC 2014 **Boston Python** PyLadies Boston

education

2010-2018 Ph.D. program in Linguistics, Massachusetts Institute of Technology

· Computational & experimental research on acquisition of Arabic morphology

· Dissertation: Biases in Segmenting Non-concatenative Morphology

· Coursework in linguistics, statistics, and machine learning

· Teaching assistant in introductory linguistics and phonology

2000-2004 **B.A.** in Linguistics and Mathematics, Cornell University

· Graduated magna cum laude and with distinction in all subjects, 4.0 GPA

· Study abroad, Fall 2003: Budapest Semesters in Mathematics

ongoing MOOCs from edX, Coursera, FutureLearn, etc.

experience

Natural Language Processing Scientist, Spirit Al 2017-now

· Build pipeline of preprocessors and classifiers for detecting toxicity in text

· Research and implement NLU algorithms for chatbot–like product

· Build in-house tools for annotating and managing data

2015-2017 Consultant, Vista Higher Learning

· Advised client on architectural design and data collection for Spanish

and French speech recognizers for second language learners

· Analyzed data to better understand corpus characteristics and recognizer performance

2008-2010 Web Developer, Imperial Consulting

· Developed custom web applications, front and back end, in Python, Django

and jQuery, for clients in education, biomedical and finance industries

External Consultant, Centre for Strategic Infocomm Technologies 2008-2009

· Advised client on evaluation procedures in speech and text processing

2004-2008 R&D Engineer, later Consultant,

Centre for Strategic Infocomm Technologies

· Researched techniques and built engines for speech recognition, language

and speaker identification, and cross-language information retrieval

· Managed projects to evaluate and acquire systems

2004 Summer Intern, PARC Palo Alto, CA

Remote

Boston, MA

Boston, MA

· Engineered a computational Lexical Functional Grammar to cover the basic sentence constructions of Modern Standard Arabic

· Built a root-and-pattern-based finite state Arabic morphological analyzer

projects

2015 Linguistic streetmap of Singapore github://michelleful/SingaporeRoadnameOrigins

> · Used machine learning (scikit-learn) and mapping technologies to create a visualization of linguistic origins of Singapore streetnames

2014 **Fuzzy Arabic Dictionary** fuzzyarabic.herokuapp.com

· Developed a novel Arabic learners' dictionary that can be gueried via non-exact transliteration, used by ~600 learners a week